Fran: Early intervention, I suppose we
can look at it in lots of different ways
because early intervention might be a bit
later in life in some respects, I think
you know, early intervention, if we talk
about when people are first talking about
suicidal feelings, instead of waiting
for people to, to be at the point where
they need to be hospitalized to just talk
about that and put in safety plans with
them and talk about what they can do if
they do start to feel those feelings.
I think that, I think
it has a massive effect.
I think just having an idea of where
you can go and not feeling so lost
with those feelings can be massive.
Tamzin: I've had really good
outcomes from young people when
they've been referred by early help.
And it's been like something
quite like easy to work with.
So it's been like this young person
wants to work on their anxiety.
This young person wants to work
on, you know, their stress and
I've found that those young people
have been ready for the support.
I had one just recently like that - I
just finished with her about a month
ago - and she was like, non-school
attender, she worked with me last year,
now going into school four days a week.
When I started working with her she
was just not even doing any days.
And then obviously wasn't engaging
with the school counselor, now
that I finished my support, she's
engaging with school counselor.
The friendships at school was
limited, now she's trying to
build up a friendship group.
So again, early intervention with
her was key because she's still,
she was, I think she was 13.
So year nine is it?
So she's still got quite a few years
of schooling to go and the GCSEs.
So with her that was really good outcomes
because early help was involved, we
had the debt relief involved with the
family, 'cause they mismanaged their
finances and we also had school support.
So it was really good outcomes
to get in early with her and do
all those 12 sessions of support.
And then at the end, you know,
she'd come right up and she was
obviously back attending school more.
Fran: I think the big thing
with an intervention for me.
And I find this with a lot of school
age children that I work with, is that
sometimes it's just learning about what
those things they're experiencing are.
So, young people get told that they're
suffering from anxiety or depression, and
then they come to me or one of the big
ones is they get told that they're angry
-  they're an angry young man - or they're
just, they've got an anger problem.
And they come to me and they're
like, "oh, I'm an angry person".
And yeah, another lad I've worked
with, so he was coming to me at 14 and
telling me he's an angry young man.
So I just talked to him about what
anger is and where it comes from.
And that nobody's
actually an angry person.
But anger's like a secondary emotion that
comes from, you know, your experiences
or things that are going on in your life.
So talk to me about understanding those
feelings of, you know, why you might
get angry sometimes, why you might throw
things around sometimes and, and what
might be leading to that was life-changing
for him in some respects, because he
just, he just thought he was an angry
person, and that was going to be how he
was going to be for the rest of his life.
But to see that, well, no, your anger
is coming from a place and your anger
is you know, there's other things you
can do instead of the things you do
when you're angry, there's things we can
teach you to learn coping mechanisms.
You know, he, he had a sort of total
breakthrough with that work and, you
know, things changed in the home.
Things changed at school.
Things changed with his partner.
Yeah, so that was, that was a
massive example of early intervention
really playing a role I think.